hello welcome to this interview with
john viveki john vavaky is
a cognitive scientist and he has become
well known
on youtube for his series on the meaning
crisis
he is also as we discovered in the early
part of the interview
a lifelong fan of science fiction and we
explore
the areas that science fiction and the
meaning crisis
overlap it's a fantastic dialogue
out of which came a real insight
into the ways that science fiction can
help us
to grow and to heal
it's really really something quite
special i really hope that you enjoy it
this interview is sponsored by
the advanced course in science fiction
and fantasy writing
the 21st century myth the interview is
also
part of the course you can
join in and help us find the new myths
for the 21st century and write your own
great science fiction
and fantasy stories you can find the
course on all good educational platforms
and you can find it on my own website
thank you very much
um so hello john thank you for taking
the time to
talk to me um i've invited you
to come and talk to me about about
science fiction
uh for an online course that i run so i
would describe myself
as uh primarily a writer and storyteller
and i do that uh for my own stories and
i work quite a lot in the business and
corporate sector
as well uh and also through my career as
i guess like an independent researcher
into storytelling
uh and with a specialization in science
fiction
uh things like uh so sci-fi
fantasy horror all of these kind of
related areas
right there's an academic called john
cloot who calls them fantastica
uh because they all have this shared
aspect of of that's cool reality
yeah i like that name that's great it's
it sounds like a place you should travel
to
well in in england the joke is that it's
a really good curry
a fantastic deca so
[Laughter]
and i have been totally totally
fascinated i'm actually having one of
those fan moments
because i've spent literally i guess
uh probably not quite hundreds of hours
but twenties or fifties of hours
watching your whole course
uh in tackling the meaning crisis
uh so i'm very used i know a lot about
you and i'm very used to watching you on
a
on my laptop screen and now here we are
talking
yeah yeah that experience has become
more more common for me i'll meet people
who will say exactly
or it's the same sort of thing that
you're saying um and uh
it's it's a very challenging experience
for me uh because i i'm by nature very
socially phobic
um and so so this sense of people
knowing me much more than i know them
when i meet them is always a little bit
like there's parts
that have this extra level of processing
i've sort of trained myself to have to
sort of like oh okay
and just sort of try and adapt into it
thank you for saying that um
i should be complaining um thank you for
saying that it's very appreciative
i really do appreciate the interest and
support a lot of people are taking in my
work
um uh it means a lot to me well it was a
really
uh important thing to do to discover for
me because
i uh and this is what i kind of want to
go into
in talking together um you know the idea
of the meaning crisis
really opened up lots of thoughts for me
about you know my own life for a start
and i'm personally struggling with this
idea of a meaning crisis
um and i feel that i found for my life
like some kind of answer to the meaning
crisis or a sense of an answer
in science fiction and fantasy right
right yeah
and these kind of escapist literatures
so i'm
i'm kind of i guess i feel like i'm
coming to you to find some kind of
wisdom
to to see if there's some kind of
overlap between these ideas
i think there is yeah um i think there's
a lot
i think um one thing i should say right
off the bat is i'm also a very
significant
uh science fiction and fantasy fan um
i i read a lot i read a lot of that
literature and i've read it
uh for very i basically from new wave on
i was reading science fiction very
deeply
um and it's it's actually had a profound
influence on me
and uh in connection with horror the
book that i wrote with
uh christopher master pietro and philip
misovich
on the meeting crisis actually uh was
possible
the title of the book they're you know
zombie zombies
it's about the zombie phenomena as a
cultural mythology for
expressing the meaning crisis so we
propose
that the zombie isn't especially the
particular version we have
um it has arisen
as a mythological way in which the
culture is trying to articulate and
express
uh the meaning crisis to itself so
horror uh also uh has had a significant
influence on my thinking about this
sure and and i think and the thing about
one of the things we might want to
explore is
uh so chris and i we've published an
article that's come out this year
on the side view we have what we call a
symptomology of the meaning crisis
where we look at various symptomatic
expressions of the meaning crisis
um and one is a phenomena that other
people have been articulating called the
virtual exodus
uh this is the fact that people are now
showing a preference for the virtual
world virtual games for example
uh like video games um
and uh and one of the things about that
is to
ask yourself what is it that people are
finding in this virtual reality
that they find so extremely lacking in
uh reality itself in actual reality um
and then one of the things i'd like to
explore because you said something that
sort of piqued my interest
and i think it was i think was somewhat
humorous on on your part
but you described um the science fiction
these literatures as escapists
but i'm wondering if right i'm wondering
if if we could compare science fiction
literature
to the virtual exodus because the
problem with the virtual exodus is it's
largely maladaptive
it seems to be associated with video
game addiction all kinds of other
deleterious effects
extended uh participation in social
media is very bad for mental health
etc etc and whether or not
i don't see science fiction necessarily
having
these deleterious effects on people and
i'm wondering if by comparison
we might be able to draw out a little
bit more
about um kind of a triangulation
approach uh compare these different
things and see what they might tell us
maybe a bit more about what's going on
in the meeting crisis
but also how science fiction may play a
role in helping people
perhaps adaptively respond to it so
maybe that's something we could explore
yeah absolutely i mean i i have some
kind of questions
prepared for you but i had the feeling
that if i ask the questions that's
probably less interesting
than just seeing what emerges from us
talking together
so right that idea of escapism
is kind of at the center of all my
questions though right
one way or another right because i see
this as
very much like a continuum of
the the overall term that gets given to
it is often nerd culture
or geek right yeah yeah these are all
things that like share this escapist
quality
they're usually fantastica in
in their their like the symbols that
they're using
and giving out to the world and it's
really interesting
that people have this sense that they
can escape into them and that there's
like a world
yeah very much they can enter into uh so
that's a huge part of science fiction
writing
so the focus of the course is on like
creating these stories
and and how do we do that um
and that's uh usually talked about in
terms of world building
so the idea that using this this
language on the page we can actually
build a world that we can enter into
could be an alien world and this really
got picked up
by video games yes very much
and all the early games that i think
back to you know things like the hobbit
these text adventures and they were so
basic when you think about them but
there was this since
we were inside them somehow and and then
and then there's this intermediate
genre of role-playing games which are
are taking on sort of increasing
uh significance uh there's a there's a
scandinavian form that is particularly
interesting to me called jeep form
in which people are doing live role
playing
and the dungeon master is actually a
director the dungeon master will come
and assign like roles to you and say
okay you're a husband and wife
and you're now right uh you you've
discovered that your wife has betrayed
you
and now act out the scene and they'll
give you things and say this is a gun
and you have to treat it as props and
they'll suddenly cut and say okay now
switch roles
and they'll do all this stuff because
what's really interesting is the
and notice how this goes the opposite
way of escape
which is why i brought it up they're
looking for a phenomena called bleed
what they want is they want the
difference between what's happening
in the game and their life to bleed
so that the distinction between them
breaks down
and the reason is that allows right it
allows the game to be a place
where they can taste they can try on
different identities
and ways of looking at the world and
and then right get them into a form that
is transferable back
to their everyday life and is in some
sense facilitary
for them solving problems that they're
finding very difficult to deal with
and what's interesting about that is
that also lines up with a lot of
literature
by my friend and colleague igor grossman
another work showing if you give people
ask people about their problems and
they'll tell you their problem blah blah
blah blah blah blah blah blah and they
almost inevitably tell it from a first
person perspective
then you then you do this to them you
say redescribe that same problem from a
third person perspective or how your
friend john
sees that problem and then they describe
it from that alternative perspective
and then they get insight on how to
solve the problem it's called the
solomon effect
and so this idea of going out and coming
back in
which bleed is really trying uh to
like deliberately create i find that
very intriguing because that speaks to
me
you that speaks to me something more
like tolkien's recovery theory of
fantasy
rather than a notion of you know just
escape
and if i'll just i'll say one more thing
no no you carry on because
when when you're doing that move when
you're doing this kind of
see when you're doing this move where
you're going out to another perspective
in order to come back and correct this
perspective
you're in uh and you know and tolkien
called that
the recovery theory right and it's a
transformation of your seeing and being
in this world that strikes me as very
very similar
to a lot of the i'm going to put these
in quotes because they're contentious
terms
a lot of the religious and spiritual
practices you see within wisdom
traditions
whereby people do some act of
self-transcendence
through some you know other world or
deeper dimension of this world
or and and that is really interesting to
me
because that seems to be reliably
correlated
i would i would argue at least
historically with people
being able to cultivate wisdom and then
i would argue based on the work that i'm
doing
the primary job wisdom has two jobs and
they're interrelated they're
interdependent jobs
it's to help you comprehensively
overcome self-deception
and to help in increase your sense of
meaning in life
and so this sense of
right this these kinds of uh
fantastica let's call them that let's
use that as a neutral term maybe
right as being right i'm proposing that
there's the continuum
that you see so yeah there's a continuum
this way with
virtual games but there's a continuum
this way if you'll allow me a spectrum
with very traditional uh religious and
spiritual practices of
self-transcendence
whereby people get to a place
where they can overcome an egocentric
perspective
that ameliorates self-deception and
enhances the sense of connectedness they
have to something
larger than themselves but also more
real than themselves
[Music]
so i said i would stop and give you a
chance to disrupt there's just so much
in there
so recovery
uh and the sense of stepping out of
ourselves in this
the spectrum from like video games
yeah to true uh like spiritual religious
ecstatic experiences yes yeah exactly
exactly yeah
yeah um like i thinking of uh
it's uh it was a documentary about uh uh
live role-playing
and the people who got into live
role-playing and the different
characters involved and what one was
like a young man
very very low self-esteem and he ended
up as the
the general in the live role-playing
game
and like two years later he was
uh hugely confident he had a family um
and he was running his own business and
it was like the experiences within the
role-playing game
that had produced this recovery for him
yeah well well think about the think
about these largely
and this is the right word fictional
worlds we take for granted when you go
into therapy
you're stepping into a fictional world
in which you're gonna the therapist is
going to
take on your being your mother or your
father
or some even some aspect of your own
personality and you're going to interact
with them
there's all this enacted symbolism that
affords
these self-transcendence people are
seeking in therapy or think about my
domain education we just we just forget
how how how weird and fictional
education is you go into this room and
you spin
well not right now but right but you
spin all these
possible worlds and i and ideas
and the whole point of that is to get
people to induce to draw from them
a new way of seeing them the world a new
way of understanding themselves
and a new way of seeing connections
between the world and themselves i mean
that's why
they were originally called the liberal
arts they're supposed to liberate us
in some important fashion they're
aspirational projects
um and so i'm very interested in
you know and and i don't and i don't
mean anything
insulting either way but like the deep
overlap between
you know religious philosophical
literature
and you know things like science fiction
and the person that really
i mean my favorite author as a kid
growing up was raj zelazny
because his work was exactly exploring
that connection right yeah i think of
like what you know what i consider
his masterpiece lord of light lord of
light is exactly
about what i'm talking about here right
and the whole point about the book and
the way it's structured
is i think at least this is my
interpretation of what zelazny was
trying to do
he was trying to create bleed he was
trying like and it woke me up
i was locked in a fundamentalist
christian worldview i'd been brought up
and i read that book and it shattered
that for me
and not because he not like sam harris
you know some new atheists come in and
gave me all these are also
it was like boom i did that thing we're
talking about where
he took me out of this perspective
opened me to
a world and i recovered this world from
it and i just realized
i can be other than i've always been
and i can see other than i've always
seen
and i experienced profound recovery i
mean that's what and so that book has
always just been
i mean i think there are other books you
might call you know maybe
i mean it won the hugo award was
nominated for nebula so it's not a
slightly amount of
piece yeah i think and so i mean for me
i mean i'm not i'm not claiming all
science fiction does this but what i'm
saying is that
there's authors that i'm attracted to
that are i think explicitly and directly
uh doing exactly what i'm talking about
they're affording
this this kind of i don't know what it
calls i don't want to call it suitable
but it's this para religious phenomena
where people are doing something like
what they used to do
you know with christianity had the whole
narrative of the passion
of the christ right and you identify
with jesus and that takes you out of
yourself
and so i i what's interesting to me
is that that that profound potential and
i'm wondering if
i'm wondering if everything on the
continuum that we've been talking about
satisfies certain hungers for meaning
but some of them do it in a maladaptive
sort of junk food version and then some
of them might be moving towards
an adaptive version of it yeah
so go ahead go ahead this is the thing
that uh like
that fascinates me and worries me at the
same time
um yeah so like uh
one of the the talks in the courses is
about star wars
and like being like seven years old i
guess
and seeing star wars on a vhs uh
cassette video machine at the time
and like i was so fascinated by the
movie that i we had to borrow the video
machine from the family who owned it
so i could watch it like five times in a
row
um but the comparison i make is that
that was probably this about the same
time as i ate my first
like cheeseburger as well and i was
really hooked by the cheeseburger in the
same way
and uh so like the history of star wars
i'm sure you're aware like the heroes
journey that's embedded in there
and where that came from and this is
like distilled from
all of our great religious myths
uh and then placed into star wars so you
could make the argument that it's like
this sacred story and it must have
intense meaning
but i also worry that it might just be
like an addictive substance like uh
that has all the appearance of meaning
but doesn't actually mean anything
and i can't find an answer to that for
myself well well
well let's try it together let's try and
work on it together right here
i mean not that not that i'm proposing
that we'll be able to solve it and why
you know but like but d logos getting
into deep
dialogue um is is very important to me
so let's look let's look at what chris
and i argued about the video games like
what
what is it they're supplying and you're
alluding to campbell and to young and
star wars right but i think there's a
there's an
uh a broader analysis that we can uh
bring in
that incorporates those insights but
extends them from cognitive science
so look what's in look what's in um
a video game so first of all there's a
narrative order
there there's a story that you
participate in into which you make a
diff
which you make a difference and that
story relates your current self to your
future self
in a clear way so there is right so it's
it's so there and so human beings have
they need places where they can play
with non-logical identity
persons are weird things we're not
identical the way to you know a coin is
identical through time by
maintaining all of its properties or
even the way two coins are identical to
each other by sharing all their
properties
i don't have any of the properties i had
when i was seven years old i don't even
have an atom in my body
that i had when i was seven years old
right i didn't know anything about
cognitive science when i was
seven-year-old
i i was a virgin and i'm not a very like
blah blah blah blah blah blah blah
right so the identity it's not a logical
or a categorical identity
and narrative is a way of practicing
non-logical identity
so that we can right relate to our
future self so narrative is
is there what else is there in the video
world well
well there's rules that world makes
sense to me like it makes sense to me i
understand it's it's ordered structure
um
so i call that a normal normal logical
order
that means the the you know the the
principles by which the world is made
intelligible to you
and you understand them and then there's
a normative order you
and this goes back to what i was saying
a few minutes ago you can self-transcend
you literally level up right you level
up and you
and as you level up you connect to your
better future self and you connect to
more important
you know deeper versions of the game
bigger scope you're ultimately going to
meet the boss
all that kind of stuff right now this
those are the
three things that religions
traditionally provided for people
religious worldview
right they gave you like you know a
narrative
here's the story here's the story and
here's how you belong to it
this is that they gave you a world view
that made sense of things
and then they told you they gave you
practices
and communities of practices and
institutions
whereby you could self-transcend
so the video games now why is that why
do we why well
think about what what what we really
want what are the things that contribute
to meaning in life
okay self transcendence this is a big
thing people
matter this is called mattering people
need to believe
with good reason i would argue that they
are connected to something larger to
them
than themselves that they matter to
something
that has a value beyond their ego sent
to predict
perspective that's very predictive of
having enhanced meaning in life
right they need right they need things
to make so
sense they need a sense of coherence
and and then finally they need a sense
of something it's called purpose or
direction
they need that narrative orientation and
so those three orders address
three of the most primary and meaning in
life is a real thing
like if you don't have meaning in life
that's predictive of suicide depression
anxiety so uh you know uh social
malfunction social media like
the opposite is the case and by the way
this is so coincidental for video games
because video games have a fourth
feature video games
are flow induction machines
right they put you into the flow state
right really really reliably
mm-hmm and and the thing about the flow
state it's
really predictive also of enhanced
meaning in life i
if you would if i if you had to ask me
you get to ask damian one
question and from that determine
how much meaning in life he has this is
the question i would ask damian
how often do you enter the flow state
not as often as i want to yeah yeah
and that's exactly the right answer
that's a good answer that's a really
good answer
so thinking about this what why what
does flow what's flow all about
well flow's all about that terrific
sense of being deeply connected
to the world of the world of having
ongoing insight
of getting a good not
not just theoretical but an an
enacted sense of being coupled to the
deeper patterns of the world
really great what's called implicit
learning so it's this connectedness
and sense-making and insight that give
people a tremendous sense
right now all of those are going on in
the video game
and they're all maladaptive because they
don't they're not set up to transfer
back to the real world
so within it's it's this weird almost
ironic paradox within the video game
you're getting everything that you want
for meaning
but you're getting it in a situation
that is not designed to transfer
so it's not like the situation of bleed
it's not like when people go to church
people go to church
and they go in to a huge sim simulation
a huge if you're this is not meant to be
insulting a huge video game
in which they're doing all of this stuff
but the idea is that's supposed to bleed
it's it's set up it's designed it's
cultivated
to transfer out and so the thing that
and sorry this is a long preamble but
i'm trying to
i think this has allowed me to formulate
a question is because i've seen work on
this
is you know is the jedi religion that
came out of star wars a real religion
right and and chris and i took this up
and some of the work we've been doing is
we want to
it's really odd about this because
you'll you'll you'll meet a lot of these
people and they're
they're they're from that demographic uh
category the nuns
n-o-n-e-s they have no are you religious
no no no and then they'll go to these
conventions and they're dressed up as
people
and they enact things and like wow
you're very religious you just don't you
just don't recognize it
so the question i want to ask it's a and
i hope this doesn't sound too simplistic
is
how much bleed is there how much
transform how much
does this participation in the star wars
world
genuinely enhance their capacity for
wisdom in their lives is it
transformative of their sense of self
their sense of world and does it afford
measurable
increase so for example if somebody is
doing a lot of star wars stuff and that
transferred such
that they were getting into the flow
state more often in their lives
or they were more capable of stepping
back and looking at their own
perspective and
transforming it that i wouldn't say it's
an addiction
i would say it's actually providing
something like recovery
sorry that was a long argument but i was
i wanted to answer your question well
no that's fantastic uh so what leaps out
of it
of it for me is that well
there's kind of like an allen watts idea
about about catholicism that catholicism
started failing people when it was
translated into english
because at the point that you couldn't
understand it you could essentially make
of it
what you wanted to and you could write
things in there
so i have an idea maybe that if the the
audience could work with
with almost anything if if they were
were wired up to take bleed from it
they could i mean i think there's i mean
i think there are
hmm i i i think
there are like essential features that
have to be in existence in an
environment
in order for it to be one in which
people can exercise cognitive agency
experience insight solve their problems
um
and you could you can see this by the
kinds of ways in which you can modify
environments and people will have very
aversive uh reactions to it
so um like i wonder about that like
let me be clear um i i'm a pluralist in
this
and that i think there are multiple ways
of setting these up so
it will work and i i think i in fact i
would argue stronger i think it has to
be that way
uh because people are in different uh
historical
cultural and environmental contexts and
so
making sense of that is going to have
variation but let me give you an analogy
of how i'm thinking about this
and maybe it'll be helpful because this
is a question that really concerns me as
a scientist
because if there aren't universals i
can't study it as a scientist
right um because that's true that's what
yeah that's what you have to have right
and there are universals about float so
flow's a good example of a universal
across
all of those differences i've mentioned
cultural linguistic
socioeconomic gender right
historical background occupation
uh personality right people when they
get into the flow state
people in all of those situations can
and they describe it in detail with
using almost the exact same words
so there's some so there's something
universal which means there's something
functional
okay so let me try and use an analogy
so the the thing i study as a scientist
and because it really links personality
intelligence
and consciousness together is a process
i call relevance realization
it's the it's this amazing ability you
have here's there's an overwhelming like
like people don't realize it's an
astronomic number
there's an overwhelming amount of
information available to you at any
moment
an overwhelming amount of information in
your long-term memory
and there's an overwhelming number of
ways you can
put sequences of behaviors together and
generate patterns of action
and yet and so you can't you can't
search all of those you can't even
search most of them
you do this really weird thing and it
sounds like a zen cohen
somehow you intelligently ignore most of
that information
and zero in on the relevant information
not not
perfectly but really really well so that
you often do the appropriate thing
in a situation and you remember the
appropriate information from your
long-term memory
and you right and what's and by the way
that
this has a lot to do with that sense of
connectedness
because here's the analogy i wanna one i
wanna make
think about the way in which evolution
is a universal process
in which you have two things at work you
have
something that's generating variation
like the number the variation within a
population
and then you have a selective process
that's cutting it down
limiting it natural selection right
competition for scarce resources and so
what you get you have is
there's a feedback loop reproduction
within it there's variation
and then there's selection and there's
variation and selection and the feedback
loop is constantly revolving with change
that's what evolution is
well your brain is doing something
analogous to that all the time you have
a sensory motor loop
you're taking in information and then
you're generating behavior even moving
your eyes around
right and so there's this constant
sensory motor loop
and notice how your brain like there's
pressure on you right now to vary
there's a pressure to be distracted and
think about other things and
oh but there's also another
countervailing one no no focus
stay connected and you're going you're
doing this all the time and you're
constantly evolving what's the relative
information
that's happening right here right now
and so you're constantly doing that now
if
if that analogy holds then i can go up
to
my the point i want to make evolution is
a universal process but it doesn't
produce the same products
everything is evolving but that doesn't
mean a shark
and a baboon are any are the same animal
they're very very different creatures
and so i think the stories we generate
can have terrific variety to them
but that doesn't mean that they're just
arbitrarily created
in the same way yep right that's what
i'm trying to get at
because because we're always engaged in
relevance realization
right right we're always having to fit
to the environment
it can't be arbitrary but it can be vast
right that's what i'm trying to get at
with a real pluralism
yeah so you know all of the
the really popular uh science fiction
stories they all have all fantastica
the these archetypal characters
and they just repeat again and again and
again across the stories
uh and you know one way that you could
interpret that perhaps slightly
cynically is maybe it's just
like some copying maybe people aren't
seeking originality in the stories
or maybe there's something else here
which is like this evolutionary
process of storytelling uh which is
going to
throw up these archetypes again and
again and again for people
yeah exactly i mean so they're
i'm not saying that jung is necessarily
wrong and we might there might be some
predispositions biologically
but it also might be something very
analogous to convergent evolution
like you look at the ixia thor which is
a reptile and you look at the dolphin
which is a mammal and they look
the same because they're in the same
environment and they've
they're in the same ecological niche and
you get convergent evolution
or you get you know different species
like radically different
you know converging on the evolution of
different kinds of eyes but
eyes keep showing up right across many
different species
right so i think it's very plausible
that there will be these archetypal
patterns
and what's interesting about them then
is they
they we should we should pay very
careful attention to them i'm not
dismissing
the possibility that there might be
laziness and formulaic thinking involved
but let's say that when that's not the
case there's the real possibility here
that you know these archetypal patterns
in story making
are not escapist because they're
actually pointing to
universal affordances of how we can
recover the world
by being more deeply connected to it by
seeing real possibilities in who we can
be
and what we can see
and that's like the the fundamental
story
of fantasy or science fiction is
becoming
somebody that we we could become exactly
some some potential we could draw out of
ourselves
yes yes but but but but
isn't that i mean
that to me strikes again it's on an
adaptive continuum with
what would it be like you know do we
sing a revival of stoicism
i i'm involved in that well stoicism is
i mean it
i mean sorry don't take this
this sounds overly simplistic and it is
it's a very complex phenomenon there's
lots going on
but if you'll allow me a bit of a slogan
just for the purposes of conversation
here
slogan stoicism is basically the
religion of internalizing socrates
right learning to see and be the way
socrates would be in situations
and that's a long practice and it takes
a lot of imaginative exercises
if you do things like the view from
above where you practice imaginatively
rising above the world
so alter your sense of what's relevant
and important you have to you know
practice redescribing things
there's all these fictional imaginable
practices you engage in
in order to internalize socrates and
that's
or you know the christians who who you
know who are internalizing christ
saint paul it's not i who live but
christ who lives within me
or the buddhists seeking to you know
realize the buddha nature within the
like that's it's the same i'm sorry but
i i see it as
like i say i see this on a continuum i
you know when i when i encounter certain
figures in
you know in what is what would be the
deep difference because many people
admit
that the picture we have of socrates
from plato and xenophon
is probably a mixture of fiction and
historically
historical accuracy right so is there
that much of a difference
between internalizing socrates and
internalizing gandalf
in order to become wiser right
i mean there's a lot more there's a lot
more philosophy developed around
socrates there's a lot more traditions
there's stoicism
and of course christianity has built up
around and then
there isn't something analogous to
gamble but i don't see why there
couldn't be right i don't see why there
couldn't be um
and and uh so
i mean the it keep for me keeps coming
back again and again and again
yes these stories don't give us
knowledge the way science and history
give us knowledge
because they're not trying to give us
knowledge they're not trying to give us
information
they're trying to afford transformation
they're giving us wisdom
and if they are really giving us wisdom
then
i don't think it's right to think of
them as addictive or escapist
at all so that
raises the question for
for a fan you know for someone who's
like living a lot of their life
um to to to assess like the value of
what they're engaging with
and maybe what i'm more interested in is
like the responsibility of a creator
right right right to tell these stories
you know maybe you're like a storyteller
in the video games industry and you have
like some kind of intuition
that these things are important but
maladaptive how would we start to think
about
making them adaptive
make making them bleed for people
well i'm actually involved in a project
with
a former student and colleague of mine
daniel greg he's
he's actually trying to design um an
online
uh live-action role-playing game with
maybe with some video elements in it
um that's designed to get people
with it is specifically designed to be
to create bleed
but not bleed at the level of your own
psychodynamic problems like in
jeep form but bleed at the level of the
cultural problems
that people are trying to wrestle with
um as they wrestle with the meeting
crisis
and so again
given i mean actuality is excellent
proof of possibility
right the fact that you know uh people
are i know somebody who's specifically
trying to do this
and i i know people on the other end uh
where you know they're they're they're
trying to create practices that
involve this kind of serious play
i don't i don't know why
well i do know sorry that i gotta
retract that because i realized what i
was about to say was just false
um if we could make a priority
to create
because there's no there's no technical
psychological reason why we couldn't
make these things
be bleed worthy and be be
set up explicitly as partake in this
and then here's also bridging practices
here's how you play the game
and then here's the practices that help
bridge you
between the game and the real world
here's an analogy i'm a martial artist
you do you do the form but you also you
know you do things like sparring and
other things you
yeah what how do you transfer it maybe
to a self-defense situation or more
importantly
like when you're doing something like
tai chi chuan you really read deeply the
dao te
chen because that's the bridging manual
that's how do i take what's
when i'm training in this very weird
ritual thing i'm doing
and make it make it bleed into my life
in fact
that happened to me one of the most
profound experiences i had i was doing a
combination of tai chi chuan
the pasta and meta and i was doing it in
graduate school and
i'm just trundling along because i was
really interested in cultivating wisdom
way back when
um and and i was pursuing it very deeply
and i wasn't really from first person's
perspective noticing that much
but i was trying to do exactly this i
was trying to get it
to be i was reading the lyric like i was
trying like i was
at least setting up the context of
making it transferable
and people started coming to me and
saying what's what are you what's going
on with you
and at first i thought oh no because in
graduate school you're afraid you're
offending other people all the time
right
right and i said what what is it what is
it and they said
you're different you write differently
you talk differently
you argue differently you're more
balanced you're more flexible
you're more responsive so what have
happened is
this very weird thing i was doing in tai
chi chuan
was bleeding out into my life there's no
reason why we can't
set these things up right what if we
read a great science fiction story and
then
put around it like how does this
transfer
how does this transfer to your life not
just idea transfer
like is there analogous things you can
do in order to try
and transfer it into your life i'm
talking with somebody right now
is becoming you know a friend of mine
nick winkelmann
he wrote a book called the language of
coaching and he his
and it's really really good he talks
about when he's trying to coach somebody
finding the analogy for them that helps
them
right transform into it's like okay so
the problem is
you need to run and you're sprinting but
you're not doing it right i need you to
sprint as if you
were an airplane taking off you'll say
that
or then and then at some point you're
now running up a hill how would you move
your leg
and imagine yourself in that and then
people
imagine that and then they recover or at
least
re like draw out the way they're
supposed to move
and see and they could do that we have
already
domains in which we're practicing how to
bridge
how to bridge how to transfer and we
have histories of doing this
this is what the religious histories and
and you know
the religious philosophies we're all
about we have the resources
we could bring them to bear there's no
reason why we couldn't build this around
like these stories right now
this makes me think of two things
uh one is like the it because i find
that
in the science fiction world there's uh
like a conflicted attitude to criticism
stories because they're things that we
love so like a critical attitude to them
it seems offensive to some people um but
there's also a love of doing this and
talking
about the stories and drawing meaning
out to them and this seems like
like the basis of a bridging activity
the the critical
yeah i think i think that for me the
questions
so this this is something i do work on
um
about what kind of things actually
affords the bridging
so let me let me sorry give me five
minutes and this will sound
like a digression but it involves
stories and it
allowed me to make a point yeah okay so
there's a there's a there's a problem
called the dunker radiation problem it's
a classic insight problem the person has
you know a tumor at the center of their
skull
uh if you try and open the skull you'll
expose them to too much infection
they'll die
right but you can beam an x-ray beam and
it won't kill them
but it will kill all the intervening
tissue when it kills the tumor
so what do you do by the way this is no
longer fiction we now do this with the
thing called the gamma knife
we lean in right okay um so it's a real
thing
and so many people like well how do i
solve this and the solution is
what you do is you break it up into a
lot of low intensity beams
that only intersect at with a at a
lethal level of intensity where the
tumor is
right so instead of one beam of lethal
intensity
you have multiple beams of sub lethal
that right that intersect just at the
point and like i said
they now literally do this with a thing
called the gamma knife when they need to
take out a small
i've seen somebody cured of lifetime
tremors where they found a little patch
of the neurons that they needed to get
rid of
and they did the gamma knife on them to
get to kill them so this is the
okay so you get the problem that's the
radiation problem yeah okay so now let's
say i'm gonna
i'm gonna i'm gonna put people in a
situation
and what i'm gonna do is i'm going to
give them a story to read
the story goes like this there's a
general who wants to attack a fortress
and the and the fortress is like at the
center
are like four causeways right that lead
to the fortress
and if the general marches his army down
any one
one of these pathways there's the
garrison in the fortress and they're
like
they're like the 300 they will come out
and like fight to the death and
right and and the general will be too
long fighting the battle he'll go out of
supply
so what does he do well he breaks his
army up into four equal components
and has them converge simultaneously on
the fortress
because as the garrison comes out to
meet any one of the four the other three
can attack the undefended fortress
and take it okay so you give people this
story
about attacking the fortress then you
give them some intervening tasks you
know
they're doing something and then you
unexpectedly give them the dunker
radiation problem right
that then they read this story
and they get no facilitation
they're no better than people who did
not read the story that's solving the
radiation problem and you say what's
going on
why not well here's the problem the
problem is
at the level of the ideas and the
propositions the two stories
are the same but that's not the kind of
transfer your brain is looking for
because think about the task the tasks
are very different
when i'm when i'm doing the generals my
task is to comprehend
an existing solution and story
but when i face the dunker radiation
problem i'm trying to
solve an unsolved problem which is a
very different task
so although propositionally the stories
are very similar
procedurally they're very very different
now there's a bunch of research showing
the opposite
if i make two things procedurally
similar
i'll get transfer i'll get powerful
transfer
and so these bridging practices they
can't be practices about just like
taking ideas from that world and
transferring them they have to do they
have to be deeper
they have to be about like that's why i
keep saying ways of seeing and ways of
being
that what's right and that's what will
transfer
like it's it's how it's how it's it's
really astonishing
how powerful um that that level
is in how much it affects transfer
the other thing that came out was uh
so so many of these stories are now like
these huge
uh corporate projects yeah
like they they cost like hundreds of
millions of dollars
and uh like i went to see the avengers
movie in in
bali when it came out and the whole
island came to a halt
for it so everyone in the world is now
like watching the same stories
but then we also think i think everyone
sees the value in like
independent creators small creators
and there's some level that we need to
actually engage with like
people who are making the stories
for us yeah that goes exactly to the
point i was making
mm-hmm right if all people are doing is
consuming
that's at the propositional level yeah
but if they don't practice the creating
and the living within it and creating it
so other people could come to live
within it
right then they're not going to get that
kind of transfer and bleed
that's why live action role playing is
so important you're not just consuming
you're also producing it especially in
situations where there's a high degree
of improvisation required
like so people people have to
i mean i think what you said is is very
astute
people have to get into a sense of like
sorry it's it's it sounds hubristic but
what it's like
like to do to create these worlds what's
it like to move
in them what's it like to critically
assess them because when you're writing
and creating
you have to engage in self-correction if
all they're ever doing is consuming the
finished product
and the idea they're like the people who
are just reading
the story of the fortress and they won't
be able to solve the
dunker radiation problem when they come
across it but if they have if you get
them to generate a solution
that's analogous then when they come to
the then they solve it
then they solve it that's what i was
trying to point to but you've
you put it better than i did right the
idea is people have to have this
participatory
relationship they have to be involved in
the process
of making it and appreciating it and
correcting it and refining it
if they're going to be afforded the
ability to
transfer from the world of science
fiction to their everyday life
well at least that's what i would argue
that's what i would argue i i
and i absolutely see it happening so
there's the
the science fiction fan community and it
calls itself fandom
and that kind of puts everyone in the
community
in a position of being a fan i guess but
when i look at that community
especially as it's formed around the
internet it's become tremendously
creative it's like yes a vast creative
community
with all different kind of levels of
engagement of how people are making
you know it might be participating in
role-playing games
and then trying to write your own novel
and yeah
that this is all a process it's not just
some creators and consumers there's a
whole process
of uh bridging from the stories
and that's fantastic
so it wouldn't take that much of
tweaking because
that i mean that's what i see i mean
i don't write fiction but i i write and
of course i appreciate this in people
who are fiction writers
i mean what let's go back to lord of
light so i mean
you could read that book is oh wow this
is just what's it like to be a god and
you know the blurring between science
fiction and fantasy and blah blah blah
or you can think and and you know and
the way
the lasne ends the book is he's he
almost hits the reader over a
head with a hammer and thing but the
point of this the point of this is to
transfer it to your life right he's like
writing he
at the end of the book so writers
when they're creating the world they're
not i at least
i would say good writers aren't creating
it to be this self-enclosed escape
they're creating it to to educate and i
mean that in a deep sense
people for their lives
right and so if if the fans aren't just
wouldn't
i want to just make this cool story but
if they tried to emulate
you know the procedures of the the
really good writers of
i want to make a story that's right will
it will
it'll be like it'll be like a great like
a great symbolic act
it'll it'll be really attractive and
draw people in
but it won't be escaped because once
they're in there they'll be changed and
transformed though
and and they'll and and it'll make them
think about
their their lives i mean it wouldn't
take that much to bring that into the
fandom
like in creating these things create
them
so that they afford recovery they afford
self-transcendence
before transformation i think that that
strikes me as
like a really adjacent possible thing uh
people could be doing right now
sure would that uh become
like in your discussions with uh jordan
hall
about the the religion that is not a
religion
yeah yeah why not exactly
yeah it could be i mean and that's what
daniel's trying to do with that with
that live-action role-playing game
he's trying to create a structure
whereby
people can engage in the religion that's
not a religion because
like like i've argued earlier and i'm
not proselytizing for any religion
but these religions are store houses and
we should treat them with reverence
because they have been preserved and and
not like not as dead museums but as
living things
right they are storehouses for
you know how to overcome self-deception
and how to afford enhanced meaning in
life that
those connections and those like that
that that deeper connectedness that
we've been talking about throughout
there they they and so why not
learn as much as we can but the
interesting thing about it
is we can play in a world where we're
not committing to any crazy whacky
metaphysics
in order to in order to cultivate the
wisdom
um in fact i was just thinking about
that that we have
so if there's a similar process uh to
like the formation of like christianity
or something you know they had
the people that had so much less access
to information
this kind of one story emerges and
everyone has to hop on board with this
story
and now we're in like this information
overload
so as a group of people doing something
similar
like all creating their own story and
everyone has like a meta awareness that
these are just stories
but we can exchange them with each other
and
they they achieve some kind of growth
you know um
that's exactly it and and if the
evolutionary analogy i gave you
earlier works in some sense correct
these stories
while being you know you know particular
to
that group are not again they're not
arbitrarily
disconnected from other stories because
there are shared processes
across the stories so you you could have
something much more
you know like a co-op where
there are different groups doing
different things but they they can
they can talk to each other they can
facilitate each other and this is
already happening
at least it's happening in relevantly
similar domains in which people are
like i get i get involved with all these
communities uh you know there's these
emerging communities around movement and
mindfulness and self-transformation
and they're all and like and they're all
emerging and i would argue and many of
them agree with me
in response to the meaning crisis and
and you have the same kind of pluralism
there's real universals between them so
they can deeply talk to each other
but there's no there's no wow but this
is the right set of practices
there's what it is is there's what i
call an ecology of practices
but just like this could be an ecology
of practices there can be an ecology of
stories
in fact there should be an ecology of
stories enmeshed within
an ecology of practices that affords the
bridging of any particular story
to a person's life and context
this seems to give like a whole new
value to things that
sometimes get get dismissed and i've
been guilty of like being dismissive
about them as
as well at times like fan fiction like
the whole process of creating
[Music]
new versions of harry potter and some of
them become really ironic and rich and
deep and
and some of them are much shallower than
that but you know there's
there's something there well i mean
there's the project
uh of internalizing harry potter the way
people internalize uh socrates
it's interesting because um
this was part of the the gnostic
tradition narcissism wasn't a religion
it's more like fundamentalism it's a
style of way in which you do various
kinds
of religion but the thing about
narcissism
and april the connect made that really
clear
in the gnostic new age and this is one
of the things that really pissed off the
emerging orthodox church
is this kind of fan fiction was part of
the practice
you were expected to generate your own
stories your own
gospels like like the the i like the
the the proliferation and i like that
because it has the word life in the
center of it
the proliferation and this is one of the
criticisms that the
the what what became the orthodox church
constantly made of the gnostics
everybody like there's this constant
proliferation of gospels and stories and
myths
and practices and you know a lot and
they saw it as just crazy chaos
but again you you see you you see that
um and for um and
so i think
it's i mean i can understand why the
church wanted to clamp it down because
it was trying to provide
you know a glue for the empire and blah
blah blah there's all these historical
reasons
but that wasn't an enormously powerful
powerful time and it it it shows that
it's possible to have a vibrant
spirituality
in which you have an ecology of stories
an ecology
of practices and you have something
deeply analogous to fan fiction
constantly going on
i'm feeling a bit mind blown because i
really love the idea of this that
something that could be drawn out of of
sci-fi fandom uh or that it's all going
on there like
implicitly and there might of course be
a tremendous healing involved with it
as well well it's the same thing what's
going on
very analogously to all these
communities i'm talking about i'm not
trying to be the founder of a religion
that's ridiculous
it's really deeply ridiculous what i
would like to do
you know and i'm trying to exemplify
with you is i'd like to provide people
with you know
the conceptual vocabulary the
theoretical grammar you know
you know ecologies of practices that are
really well vetted in terms of our
cutting-edge cognitive science
to help people write explicate
what's already implicit and emerging and
communicate
and coordinate and you know and even
curate that's what i think is a real
possibility that's what excites me
because we need i mean uh now i'll be a
a little bit more i don't know what to
say i've been serious throughout but
maybe a little bit more dour
we need to address the meaning crisis we
really do
and i mean first of all the amount of
suffering it's causing is tremendous
um and it's been exacerbated very
significantly i would argue by covid
um and the meaning crisis
is really really weakening us
almost like an illness at a profound
level of our cognition and our agency so
that we can't deal with the other
pressing issues that are are really
threatening us with you know you know
serious
loss of life potential extinction i
don't mean to sound alarmist or anything
but there's a lot of stuff that's
happening right now and i mean and the
interesting thing is as you know
science fiction often addresses these
these concerns
very very deeply very profoundly uh and
so
i think if we have to
and this is why you know and this is
part of the discussions i have with
jordan jordan hall
because his main argument is this meta
crisis is not only accelerating the rate
of its acceleration is
is increasing right it is right we have
to we have to
coordinate and actualize and invent
everything we can as massively and as
parallel
and as dynamically as we can right now i
would argue and
you know i do think there's a potential
in what we've been talking about
and if we could actualize that and
direct it towards
um stealing the culture um
i think that would be fantastic i i
would do everything
i could in my power to try and help
bring that about
there's something in jordan hall's
acceleration upon acceleration that is
quite science fictional in itself
yeah exactly yeah yeah
very much i'm thinking very much yeah
and we had to be able to understand that
with stories
you like a singularity kind of demands
constantly remaking the story
that is making sense yes because that's
exactly fine
yeah and that's exactly that and so
jordan and i have talked about how that
brings with it
like there's a faith in these stories
it's a different kind
uh well it's in i would say it's the one
of the older meanings of faith
faith is just has become this assertion
of things you shouldn't believe sort of
like
asserting things that don't have good
evidence or reason behind them um
um but there's a there's an older
meaning and it's still present in our
word faithfulness
like me being faithful to my partner
doesn't mean that i believe
crazy things about her it means that
i couple myself so that i'm constantly
renewing
what i can be and how i can see her so
she can constantly grow
in how she can be and we are committed
to that we are faithful to each other
we're trying to maintain a continuity of
contact not give
some final version of anything we're not
trying to give a final
solution ominous words there or a final
story about anything
that's not what being faithful means at
all and so jordan and i talk about the
way
right this on go again similar to the
gnostics right this process of
ongoing re re-inventio
the the latin word invention inventio
doesn't mean it
it means simultaneously to create and to
discover so i'd like to use that term
you know the constant inventio of new
stories
that keep us faithful to a reality that
is itself
undergoing significant change the way i
am faithful
to this very complex being
called my my my lover right she is
right she's incredibly complex as any
person is
that's and alicia yoraro talks about
this
you know what stories are really good
for uh she's one of the people that did
a lot of important work on the nature of
dynamical systems
stories get you formatting your your
cognition
so that you are in the right form of
information processing
for tracking dynamical systems and so if
the world is
right this massively complex
self-organizing dynamical mess
which it is we need stories that are
themselves recursively changing
so that we can track that in
a week we can maintain a continuity of
contact
we can be faithful to that ever-changing
reality
and so again i think science fiction and
fantasy
point the way uh for doing that sort of
thing
we've been talking for a little bit over
over an hour i don't want to take up too
much of your time
uh well i mean i i can talk for another
10 15 minutes or so
but yeah but i don't i don't i don't
always i also don't want to be imposing
so no no that's fine because i i there's
another question i'd like to ask and i
think
we're also like just on the edge of
something really interesting
which uh
kind of this recursive nature of stories
so that seems to be in
science fiction absolutely science
fiction writers are looking really
closely at
the the point of the world where it's
changing
yeah like stitch new metaphors around it
and then those stories are like being
brought back into a community
who are either accepting them or
rejecting them
and then putting them into the world
and i think that relates to the question
i wanted to ask because
um you know i i've like spoken to like
quite well-known physicists
you know and they secretly tell me about
their interest in science fiction
yes uh like uh and you know you yourself
you said you're a big science fiction
fan and i assume
like you would be so it's kind of there
in our intellectual life
but we also feel like we can't like talk
about it or put it at the center
of of things that we're doing quite
often i'm interested in why
that is sometimes maybe you have some
experience of why
i do and i i want to explore that with
you because i think that's a wonderful
question
because i want to do what i've done
before i want to set it into a bigger
family of where people do that
because there's other things that people
won't talk about
but have a profound impact even on how
they do their science you know there's
like 40
of the population have mystical
experiences
yeah right or right or these profound
experiences of awe
and transformative experiences and if
you like
if you get if you take somebody out and
have a dinner with a scientist and
you know give them perhaps a little bit
of wine and let like and get them
why did you get into this first i'll
give you the career answer the one that
they have to put on this cv
right blah blah blah but wait and go and
then you'll get
no no they're actually they're actually
wrestling with problems of meaning
right and making sense and they're also
right
there's been often something that really
they had a moment where they had a
realization
and you know both in the sense of
they're aware and and also the sense of
being connected to what's more real and
that really
uh drives them um and yet
we don't talk about these experiences
because they're not part of
the sort of i don't know what to call it
the enlightenment model of how the mind
works
which is right this model that the mind
is this
uh monolithic monological thing
that right works best on its own and
it's
self-sufficient and this is all [ __ ]
by the way
i mean it's really not true about how we
work
um and uh so
we that doesn't have to be the case
if you go back far enough like even just
before
in the renaissance you can see it but
farther back you can also see it
uh when you had like a neoplatonic world
view people thought it was
very vitally important that their
spirituality and their scientific
practice
were deeply interwoven mutually
explicated and mutually afforded
but for various historical reasons that
i go over in the series
right awakening for the meeting crisis
we've now got a place where those are
oppositional to each other
and the thing about it here's what i'm
good the thing about it i'm going to
propose to you damian
is science fiction has enough and we've
been talking about it all throughout
today
it has it's it's close enough maybe not
at the ideal level but really at the
procedural and existential level
it's close enough to a and
self-transcendence
and all of this stuff it's right even
trying to induce ah
right and you know and god-like beings
can show up in it and you know
and people can undergo radical
transformation like
all of that that's just too close
to spirituality and religion and
mystical experiences
and all that kind of stuff and you don't
take that
seriously right you don't take that
seriously because
even though it's not true we think
that you know scientists are these like
so and i i want to make another point
because it has to do with current work
i'm doing about scientists
and exactly this kind of thing and this
is work i'm doing with dan shapi
so you've got the nasa scientists
literal rocket scientists in some sense
who are moving around the rovers on mars
like your spirit
and opportunity right they're moving the
rovers around now because of the
of the of the delay there's no joystick
control
there's no joystick control so it's not
like a video game at all what they do is
they get
batches of black and white pictures
right that they
pour over and then they send back
batches of command
and there's all this delay so you that
sounds all very abstract and cold
but what do they look for they
what what are they looking for when they
try to hire somebody into the group this
goes to some of the
ethnography done by for testing another
they look for people who can generate
this
experience they feel like they're on
mars
a sense of being on mars they can
somehow right which is exactly what
people want in the video game right that
sense of presence
the sense it's real because i'm i'm in
it i'm there
i am in the video world it doesn't have
to do with how real the video world is
because people can get the uh that sense
of presence in things like tetris
so how are these scientists getting this
sense of being
on mars and why is that so important
well they do this
really weird stuff they do this stuff
like this
first of all they identify with the the
rover they'll say
i need to go here or we need to go there
or i can't move my wheel right now
and and so they don't say the rover they
first of all they so they
anthropomorphize the rover
but they also technomorphize themselves
so they do stuff like this they'll say
okay uh they'll put the phone put the
phone in front of them and they'll say
oh wait there's a rock and they'll put
their hands up like this and say and
they're on a swivel chair
i need to like in these and they do and
they what they do is they they enact
remember symbolically enacted they enact
being the rover
they unhacked it right they enact it
right they technomorphize themselves
and this gets so weird right they'll say
and i wish i had it up but this is like
i've got talks online if people want to
see it where i actually read the literal
quotes
so i'm not you know i'm not ex i'm not
exaggerating here
they'll say stuff like this you know i
was working in the garden
and my my my right wrist kept hurting me
and went and then i got to the lab and
rover's right wheel wasn't working
properly
and you know i'm not saying it's magic
but there's some kind of
except they do this weird stuff
now they don't put any of that in the
articles they publish
yeah of course not but all of that
enacted
symbolism all of that bleed
is what they're looking for because that
actually gives people knowing what it's
like to be on mars
and that enables them to do the field
work
do the science but we don't report it
any of that because no no no
and and but but but that's what they're
actually doing in order to do the
science
so with the line there between them
doing the science
and something paul anderson like wrote
a really classic science fiction story
call me joe
right where he's sort of like he's sort
of connecting to some biological avatar
on a planet to do exploration
and eventually the identity between him
and that biological avatar breaks down
and he right it's the same thing with
the scientists
it's the same thing with the scientists
and the rover yeah
well there's something like really
interesting in science fiction
just in like the two words for science
and fiction it is this meeting
of yeah exactly the these things that
are shouldn't be mixed yeah
you know and there's there's a whole
spectrum of people who are into science
fiction
and there's there's a solid group of
people who are like the hard science
fiction fans
and they consciously they just want the
book to just
expand on ideas from science and there's
like an annoyance or an anger if it does
something fantastical around that
and i can see a really good reason for
that because you want to look just at
this point
of what's changing in the world so
that's a relative reason
and i can also see that there's like
something
within yourself that you're trying not
to acknowledge
in that yeah exactly as well
but i love what you just said i hadn't
thought about it that
that way but that's brilliant symbol on
means to join together
the greek word symbol and you the word
like science fiction is joy
you said we're joining together the
things that shouldn't be joined together
but of course that's what all symbolic
behavior does
um i hadn't thought about that that's
really good
that's really good so i guess maybe one
way of
encapsulating what i've been saying to
you is we should be joining them
together
we should we should and um
i understand why people like uh hard
science fiction
i get that but the problem with hard
uh is well not not not problem because
there's nothing
problematic about it one thing that
what that i would find problematic is
people being imperial about it saying
only this counts or something like that
is
when i look at the hard science fiction
from the 1950s it seems so stupid
now because the science right the
science that they thought
was going to be the unchallenged science
has been massively
challenged and overturned um and
and the fact that there's also now
there's like some of our sciences like
biology and cognitive science
are going through almost all almost
revolutionary
changes um in there and the
understanding
and so people should perhaps be
a little bit looser about the commitment
to the metaphysics
uh within a scientific world view
now i under like i'm not i'm not
espousing irrationalism or anything
ridiculous like this
but
what's the worry with uh with science
fiction that's a little bit more
speculative
is it that you're
and you alluded to this what's it what's
like what's the what's what's wrong with
it like
uh because it's not real that can't be
the answer because it's
all of its scientific like what's the
concern maybe i should ask you instead
of
making it a rhetorical question what do
you think like you you have more
familiarity with this
with this group than i do like i said i
i cut my teeth on new wave
and new wave was the critical response
to hard sci-fi
right right right so i've always been
i i i maybe i should be i mean i've read
some of the hard sci-fi like highland
and
other people earlier people like that
but actually when you when you go
looking for it it's very difficult to
really find
hard science yeah because science
fiction will ins
just insist on becoming fantasy
in some way it just yeah and it's like
however much you try to limit yourself
to just like a purely materialist idea
of the world your imagination is gonna
like escape around it and
i think what's happening is that uh
there's lots of of personal fantasies
that really appeal to people who are
uh just to that that hard science
fiction mindset
so actually what's going on inside the
story is like the fulfillment of lots of
personal fantasies right
not actually being a robot that isn't
somebody's fantasy but there's something
in that
that yeah right expresses that
so you it's a way of saying that like my
fantasy
is very real and important and other
people's fantasies
aren't oh so it's just narcissism
well i think there's a little bit of
that in there a little bit
but it it's probably very difficult to
escape because
you know you're you you're having
reinforced
the uh well you've been told by the
culture that your world view is
completely correct
right right already and it's very
difficult to get out of that
i think unless something breaks you out
of it
but but i mean for me again and maybe
people don't agree with this
for me it's the philosophical and i mean
that in both senses
i mean philosophical in the way we
currently use it meaning this you know
reflection
on you know people's epistemological and
metaphysical frameworks
but i also mean it in the action sense
of the
ilia sophia the the the the collective
love
the shared love for wisdom i mean in
both senses of it
that to me the philosophical potential
of science fiction is
is is the real potential we've been
talking about here together
and and and right it if you aren't
willing to step back
and at least in a symbolic world
you know question your metaphysics and
your epistemology
and how you are aspiring to being a
better more virtuous self
i mean how else are you going to do it i
mean
i i mean it's like i mean
i'm sorry i i i i i'm getting really
presumptuous i'm maybe even pretentious
and i don't mean to be but
i'm trying i'm trying uh i'm trying to
ask a genuinely sympathetic question
aren't you condemning yourself to kind
of a philosophically impoverished
way of being and that seems to me to be
a very dangerous thing
i'm a scientist so theories are going to
come and go
what ultimately matters i mean what
matters existentially for me
is not the knowledge i
have but
the understanding i can cultivate and
ultimately
the wisdom that i might to some degree
realize that's what matters to me
and i think that's the the fight that
science fiction has been having with
itself
from from the uh one words really
were the people who were starting to say
that we had this thing this meeting of
science and fiction
and we think there's something really
important here but
you're only using it for this one
[Music]
framework this this one in the world and
we can open it to many many
more ways of seeing the world um
like i don't know if you have any
awareness of like uh the hugo awards
yeah or what happened with them
politically over like the last no i
don't i don't know about that
no what happened well there were they've
always been
uh like statistically very dominated by
men uh white american culture
right right and there's been like a huge
culture war over them
significantly before it manifested like
more broadly
across the culture oh nice period
uh and it was really you know the
uh about diversity that was the word
that you'd give it
in the awards but it really was about
intellectual diversity you know
what are we actually talking about uh
in science fiction uh and that was like
a huge
a huge fight online i was writing about
it for the guardian at the time
so it was uh it was very interesting to
lipro and i could see it
kind of mirroring out into the broader
culture right right
wow that's really pressing it that's
really interesting
that's really cool i remember
hitting like i don't read as much as i
used to because i'm
so busy um
but i i remember i guess
i i i see it retrospectively now like i
was bumping up against something when i
read ancillary justice
and i was getting that in from that that
book
uh even the way she's using pronouns in
that book oh that was like
the book that defines
that that latest kind of shift in
science fiction
right right done a lot cyberpunk had
done a lot
but it was still kind of very
monocultural
ancillary justice was like the the
breakthrough of a lot of women writers
and writers of color all happened around
that time
right right and science fiction is much
more interesting
for it like it's truly fascinating at
the moment
what's being made science fiction fields
it's impossible to keep track of as well
because there's just far too much
happening
uh well yeah we have the proliferation
of pluralism uh but again that doesn't
mean that
it has to that doesn't connote or have
to connect or even denote
chaos i mean there's a possibility like
we've talked about earlier
about it about of there being
cooperative
uh coordination uh between all of these
different aspects
have you ever been to uh a world con
science fiction community i i i've been
to
uh i don't i haven't been to a science
fiction world and i've been to like a
comic-con
and okay like that uh very similar in a
lot of ways
yeah uh and and i was just i remember
that went into the the book chapter that
chris and philip and i wrote because i'd
come away from one of those
and i went and i said i've just been in
this like i was just
like overwhelmed by how religious and i
think that's the right word
this event was and it was like wow
wow i mean if if if if christianity
could tap into this
the churches would be packed right uh
and it was like so yeah i have been and
i like it
it had this um just a huge impression on
me
i guess christianity's problem is that
it's really not into fan fiction
it doesn't well because it's pretty
suppressed gnostics
yeah that shouldn't have that was his
maybe that's his big long-term mistake
maybe at the time that was the right
thing to do but long-term
it really really it really pays i mean
and you see and you see this coming out
right in kind of a shadow side you see
protestantism and then the
endless proliferation ongoing
accelerating proliferation of protestant
denominations
yes it's like it's like it's like this
gnostic underbelly
came back and resurfaced in this
profound way
wow so like the the like the internecine
warfare between
religious denominations well it's very
similar you have like
sub-genres of science
um thank you very like wow
really thank you for this discussion
john i'm
really blown away well well thank you
very much
um uh you know
i i want you to have of course complete
priority for this for your
for your course your podcast but if at
some point
um you could share the recording with me
i'd love to load uh upload this on my
channel too
i'll just give it to you go ahead and do
that yeah okay
because i i think i mean this touches in
so many areas that i
i would like to have been speaking to uh
but
you know but never have because
so thank you i i thought this was just
really
really wonderful yeah damian you you
so i have a definition of deal logos
theologus is when the participants get
to a place
collectively that they couldn't get to
individually and i
felt that very much in my discussion
with you yeah and
so thank you very much this is the first
interview i've done for the course and i
really wanted it to be with you because
uh
i had a feeling that all of this kind of
stuff would come out of it just an
intuition
well your intuition was very forsightful
um and uh i mean
i i i saved this book uh because he's
dead now
i hadn't read it before um what's what
is it
uh a night in the lonesome october it's
one of zelazny's last books
and it's actually each chapter is a day
in october
um and it's a fantasy book and so i'm
reading it in october
uh but i talking to you about all of
this
really sort of also stirred up a lot of
well a lot of my memories and some very
cherished ones around this and it's
actually really nice that i'm reading
this book and had that conversation with
you so
at a very personal level this was a very
enriching conversation for me so thank
you very much
thank you i'm really happy it's been
such a good talk um
i would if there's like ways of talking
about this more in future i would be
super interested in doing that so count
me in
just let me know count me in i like this
was valuable
uh this was good this was enriching i
would i would be
and it was it was a pleasure speaking
with you i'd love to do this again at
some point
okay great thank you very much i'm gonna
let you go
get about your day well thank you very
much
take good care damien